Old Letters Club Records, 1926-1937
Smith College Archives
Old Letters Club Records
1926-1937
Old Letters Club
RG 80 UUID:6023499f-7108-4e36-b6b6-5e8211b3d25d
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Club to collect historical letters. Contains letters written between 1776 and 1871.
Students in the History Department founded this club with the help of Professor John Spencer Bassett in 1926. The purpose of the club was to collect a diverse group of letters, not necessarily valuable, that documented the lives of women and men throughout history. Members of the club accumulated the material in the collection over several years from various sources and donors. See Folder 1a "General Information" for more details on the club and its purpose.
The Old Letters Club records, consisting of 5 linear inches, are a small collection of letters written between 1776 and 1871, with the bulk of the collection composed in the mid-eighteenth century. Extremely diverse with many of the letters written around the Revolutionary and Civil wars by both women and men, the letters collected by the club are not only of a personal nature, but encompass business and legal affairs as well. According to the club's purpose, many of the letters provide insight into the daily lives of people at different points in history; however, none of the series of letters are complete, some of the authors cannot be identified, and none of the signatures are well-known. The collection is not arranged chronologically; instead, the club's original method of arrangement by donor and then accession is maintained. As many of the letters were given on loan to the original club, there is a gap in the middle of the collection where thirteen letters are missing as well as another gap towards the end of the collection where an additional thirty-three letters are unaccounted for. Included in the files are both the club's original index cards documenting the letters and the index cards created by an archivist while processing the collection. Some of the information differs between the cards and the file folders because of new dates and names discovered upon a closer reading of the letters. Every letter has a corresponding index card except for letter # 147.
Note: This collection is part of 80. Student Clubs and Organizations
The collection is not arranged chronologically; instead, the club's original method of arrangement by donor and then accession is maintained.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
History of the Collection
Search Terms
Old Letters Club (Smith College); Letters--United States.; United States--History--1775-1865--Sources.
- general information May 1926, May 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- index cards undated (Box 1, Folder 1b)
- Leon Camphey ? Feb. 2, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 1c)
- ? Nichols Feb. 12, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- G.E. Pugh Sept. 5, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- G.E. Pugh Feb. 4, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- A. Holbrook June 21, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- G.E. Pugh Jan. 29, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Leonard Dye Feb. 18, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Leonard Dye Sept. 14, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Leonard Dye Aug. 7, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Leonard Dye Sept. 27, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Leonard Dye Mar. 18, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- W. Frampton ? May 16, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Leonard Dye Sept. 24, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Leonard Dye Jan. 1, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Leonard Dye Feb. 10, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Leonard Dye July 25, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- James Birell Apr. 28, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- W.W.V. Buchanan May 29, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Peter Wefler July 26, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- F.W. Foster Jan. 31, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- M. Laurence July 7, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- W.W.V Buchanan Jan. 29, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Rev. Harold Bridge Aug. 17, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Samuel B. Stivers Sept. 21, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Garret Howell July 16, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Garret Howell Mar. 15, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Alexander E. Stivers Apr. 28, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Alexander E. Stivers May 20, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Alexander E. Stivers July 8, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Alexander E. Stivers July 14, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Alexander E. Stivers Aug. 13, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Alexander E. Stivers Oct. 20, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Alexander E. Stivers May 16, 1864? (Box 1, Folder 33)
- George Smith May 17, 1813 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Samuel Hutchinson June 3, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Eliza Thornton June ?, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- ? June 30, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- missing undated (Box 1, Folder 38-50)
- J.C. Herken undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
- ? Nov. 6, 1830 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- ? Feb. 7, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- ? July 7, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Clementine Stanwood Aug. 24, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Clementine Stanwood Dec. 29, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Clementine Stanwood Aug. 5, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Clementine Stanwood Aug. 25, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Clementine Stanwood Nov. 8 ?, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Clementine Stanwood Dec. 8 ?, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- Clementine Stanwood Sept. 30, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Elnathan P. Hathaway Feb. 21, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- L.C. Paerin Feb. 7, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Juda Gale May 27, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- L. Ingalls March 22, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- Rev. Whitman Metcalf undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
- Juda Gale Dec. 9, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Arrin Dodge Nov. 11, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- Rev. Whitman Metcalf June 16, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- J. Darling Oct 9, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- J. Darling Dec. 20, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 71)
- ? Dec. 27, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 72)
- S. Phipps March 13, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 73)
- ? June 10, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Gen. Huntington Nov. 16, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- Tim Edwards June 17, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 76)
- missing undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
- Barnabas Deane Sept. 30, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- J. Trumbull July 5, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- Tench Tilghman Oct., 29 1779 (Box 1, Folder 80)
- Sam B. Webb Nov. 16, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- Col. Hugh Hughes June16, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 82)
- Samuel H. Parsons Nov. 14, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 83)
- J. Trumbull Aug. 2, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Dan Putnam Jan. 10, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 85)
- Maj. Dumas Nov. 14, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 86)
- Oliver Ellsworth May 23, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 87)
- D. Humphrys May 14, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 88)
- Gen. Sam Parsons Jan. 14, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 89)
- Maj. D. Humphrys March 1, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 90)
- W. Rondineau ? June 20, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 91)
- J. Trumbull Dec. 23, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 92)
- Samuel Parsons Nov. 25, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 93)
- Daniel Putnam May 23, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 94)
- Daniel Putnam June 29, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 95)
- Judge Putnam July 8, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 96)
- Jennie Howell ? undated (Box 1, Folder 97)
- Harriet ? May 5, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 98)
- Isaac Child March 23, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 99)
- D. Hutchinson July 29, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 100)
- missing undated (Box 1, Folder 101)
- Michael Egan Feb. 24, 1850 (Box 1, Folder 102)
- William and Ann Hayes Aug. 8, 1855, Dec. 20, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 103-109)
- James Egan Aug. 25, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 110)
- James Egan Mar. 11, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 111)
- James Egan May 22, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 112)
- missing undated (Box 1, Folder 113-146)
- Nathaniel West Nov. 17, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 147)